Minimum number of jumps to reach end

Given an array of integers where each element represents the max number of steps that can be made forward from that element. Write a function to return the minimum number of jumps to reach the end of the array (starting from the first element). If an element is 0, then cannot move through that element.

Example:

 
Input: arr[] = {1, 3, 5, 8, 9, 2, 6, 7, 6, 8, 9}
Output: 3 (1-> 3 -> 8 ->9)
 

First element is 1, so can only go to 3. Second element is 3, so can make at most 3 steps eg to 5 or 8 or 9.

Method 1 (Naive Recursive Approach)
A naive approach is to start from the first element and recursively call for all the elements reachable from first element. The minimum number of jumps to reach end from first can be calculated using minimum number of jumps needed to reach end from the elements reachable from first.

minJumps(start, end) = Min ( minJumps(k, end) ) for all k reachable from start

 
#include <stdio.h>
#include <limits.h>

// Returns minimum number of jumps to reach arr[h] from arr[l]
int minJumps(int arr[], int l, int h)
{
   // Base case: when source and destination are same
   if (h == l)
     return 0;

   // When nothing is reachable from the given source
   if (arr[l] == 0)
     return INT_MAX;

   // Traverse through all the points reachable from arr[l]. Recursively
   // get the minimum number of jumps needed to reach arr[h] from these
   // reachable points.
   int min = INT_MAX;
   for (int i = l+1; i <= h && i <= l + arr[l]; i++)
   {
       int jumps = minJumps(arr, i, h);
       if(jumps != INT_MAX && jumps + 1 < min)
           min = jumps + 1;
   }

   return min;
}

// Driver program to test above function
int main()
{
  int arr[] = {1, 3, 6, 3, 2, 3, 6, 8, 9, 5};
  int n = sizeof(arr)/sizeof(arr[0]);
  printf("Minimum number of jumps to reach end is %d ", minJumps(arr, 0, n-1));
  return 0;
}
 

If we trace the execution of this method, we can see that there will be overlapping subproblems. For example, minJumps(3, 9) will be called two times as arr[3] is reachable from arr[1] and arr[2]. So this problem has both properties (optimal substructure and overlapping subproblems) of Dynamic Programming.

Method 2 (Dynamic Programming)
In this method, we build a jumps[] array from left to right such that jumps[i] indicates the minimum number of jumps needed to reach arr[i] from arr[0]. Finally, we return jumps[n-1].

 
#include <stdio.h>
#include <limits.h>

int min(int x, int y) { return (x < y)? x: y; }

// Returns minimum number of jumps to reach arr[n-1] from arr[0]
int minJumps(int arr[], int n)
{
    int *jumps = new int[n];  // jumps[n-1] will hold the result
    int i, j;

    if (n == 0 || arr[0] == 0)
        return INT_MAX;

    jumps[0] = 0;

    // Find the minimum number of jumps to reach arr[i]
    // from arr[0], and assign this value to jumps[i]
    for (i = 1; i < n; i++)
    {
        jumps[i] = INT_MAX;
        for (j = 0; j < i; j++)
        {
            if (i <= j + arr[j] && jumps[j] != INT_MAX)
            {
                 jumps[i] = min(jumps[i], jumps[j] + 1);
                 break;
            }
        }
    }
    return jumps[n-1];
}

// Driver program to test above function
int main()
{
    int arr[] = {1, 3, 6, 1, 0, 9};
    int size = sizeof(arr)/sizeof(int);
    printf("Minimum number of jumps to reach end is %d ", minJumps(arr,size));
    return 0;
}
 

Output:

 Minimum number of jumps to reach end is 3 

Thanks to parasfor suggesting this method.

Time Complexity: O(n^2)

Method 3 (Dynamic Programming)
In this method, we build jumps[] array from right to left such that jumps[i] indicates the minimum number of jumps needed to reach arr[n-1] from arr[i]. Finally, we return arr[0].

 
int minJumps(int arr[], int n)
{
    int *jumps = new int[n];  // jumps[0] will hold the result
    int min;

    // Minimum number of jumps needed to reach last element
    // from last elements itself is always 0
    jumps[n-1] = 0;

    int i, j;

    // Start from the second element, move from right to left
    // and construct the jumps[] array where jumps[i] represents
    // minimum number of jumps needed to reach arr[m-1] from arr[i]
    for (i = n-2; i >=0; i--)
    {
        // If arr[i] is 0 then arr[n-1] can't be reached from here
        if (arr[i] == 0)
            jumps[i] = INT_MAX;

        // If we can direcly reach to the end point from here then
        // jumps[i] is 1
        else if (arr[i] >= n - i - 1)
            jumps[i] = 1;

        // Otherwise, to find out the minimum number of jumps needed
        // to reach arr[n-1], check all the points reachable from here
        // and jumps[] value for those points
        else
        {
            min = INT_MAX;  // initialize min value

            // following loop checks with all reachable points and
            // takes the minimum
            for (j = i+1; j < n && j <= arr[i] + i; j++)
            {
                if (min > jumps[j])
                    min = jumps[j];
            }      

            // Handle overflow 
            if (min != INT_MAX)
              jumps[i] = min + 1;
            else
              jumps[i] = min; // or INT_MAX
        }
    }

    return jumps[0];
}
 

Time Complexity: O(n^2) in worst case.

Thanks to Ashishfor suggesting this solution.

Please write comments if you find anything incorrect, or you want to share more information about the topic discussed above.

Source

http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/minimum-number-of-jumps-to-reach-end-of-a-given-array/

Category: Arrays Tags: Dynamic Programming

Post navigation

← Count smaller elements on right side Populate Inorder Successor for all nodes →

Writing code in comment? Please use code.geeksforgeeks.org, generate link and share the link here.

Dynamic Programming | Set 11 (Egg Dropping Puzzle)

The following is a description of the instance of this famous puzzle involving n=2 eggs and a building with k=36 floors.

Suppose that we wish to know which stories in a 36-story building are safe to drop eggs from, and which will cause the eggs to break on landing. We make a few assumptions:

…..An egg that survives a fall can be used again.
…..A broken egg must be discarded.
…..The effect of a fall is the same for all eggs.
…..If an egg breaks when dropped, then it would break if dropped from a higher floor.
…..If an egg survives a fall then it would survive a shorter fall.
…..It is not ruled out that the first-floor windows break eggs, nor is it ruled out that the 36th-floor do not cause an egg to break.

If only one egg is available and we wish to be sure of obtaining the right result, the experiment can be carried out in only one way. Drop the egg from the first-floor window; if it survives, drop it from the second floor window. Continue upward until it breaks. In the worst case, this method may require 36 droppings. Suppose 2 eggs are available. What is the least number of egg-droppings that is guaranteed to work in all cases?
The problem is not actually to find the critical floor, but merely to decide floors from which eggs should be dropped so that total number of trials are minimized.

Source: Wiki for Dynamic Programming

In this post, we will discuss solution to a general problem with n eggs and k floors. The solution is to try dropping an egg from every floor (from 1 to k) and recursively calculate the minimum number of droppings needed in worst case. The floor which gives the minimum value in worst case is going to be part of the solution.
In the following solutions, we return the minimum number of trails in worst case; these solutions can be easily modified to print floor numbers of every trials also.

1) Optimal Substructure:
When we drop an egg from a floor x, there can be two cases (1) The egg breaks (2) The egg doesn’t break.

1) If the egg breaks after dropping from xth floor, then we only need to check for floors lower than x with remaining eggs; so the problem reduces to x-1 floors and n-1 eggs
2) If the egg doesn’t break after dropping from the xth floor, then we only need to check for floors higher than x; so the problem reduces to k-x floors and n eggs.

Since we need to minimize the number of trials in worst case, we take the maximum of two cases. We consider the max of above two cases for every floor and choose the floor which yields minimum number of trials.

 
  k ==> Number of floors
  n ==> Number of Eggs
  eggDrop(n, k) ==> Minimum number of trails needed to find the critical
                    floor in worst case.
  eggDrop(n, k) = 1 + min{max(eggDrop(n - 1, x - 1), eggDrop(n, k - x)): 
                 x in {1, 2, ..., k}}
 

2) Overlapping Subproblems
Following is recursive implementation that simply follows the recursive structure mentioned above.

 
# include <stdio.h>
# include <limits.h>

// A utility function to get maximum of two integers
int max(int a, int b) { return (a > b)? a: b; }

/* Function to get minimum number of trails needed in worst
  case with n eggs and k floors */
int eggDrop(int n, int k)
{
    // If there are no floors, then no trials needed. OR if there is
    // one floor, one trial needed.
    if (k == 1 || k == 0)
        return k;

    // We need k trials for one egg and k floors
    if (n == 1)
        return k;

    int min = INT_MAX, x, res;

    // Consider all droppings from 1st floor to kth floor and
    // return the minimum of these values plus 1.
    for (x = 1; x <= k; x++)
    {
        res = max(eggDrop(n-1, x-1), eggDrop(n, k-x));
        if (res < min)
            min = res;
    }

    return min + 1;
}

/* Driver program to test to pront printDups*/
int main()
{
    int n = 2, k = 10;
    printf ("\nMinimum number of trials in worst case with %d eggs and "
             "%d floors is %d \n", n, k, eggDrop(n, k));
    return 0;
}
 

 
Output:
Minimum number of trials in worst case with 2 eggs and 10 floors is 4
 

It should be noted that the above function computes the same subproblems again and again. See the following partial recursion tree, E(2, 2) is being evaluated twice. There will many repeated subproblems when you draw the complete recursion tree even for small values of n and k.

 

                         E(2,4)
                           |                      
          ------------------------------------- 
          |             |           |         |   
          |             |           |         |       
      x=1/\          x=2/\      x=3/ \    x=4/ \
        /  \           /  \       ....      ....
       /    \         /    \
 E(1,0)  E(2,3)     E(1,1)  E(2,2)
          /\  /\...         /  \
      x=1/  \               .....
        /    \
     E(1,0)  E(2,2)
            /   \
            ......

Partial recursion tree for 2 eggs and 4 floors.
 

Since same suproblems are called again, this problem has Overlapping Subprolems property. So Egg Dropping Puzzle has both properties (see thisand this) of a dynamic programming problem. Like other typical Dynamic Programming(DP) problems, recomputations of same subproblems can be avoided by constructing a temporary array eggFloor[][] in bottom up manner.

Dynamic Programming Solution
Following is C/C++ implementation for Egg Dropping problem using Dynamic Programming.

 
# include <stdio.h>
# include <limits.h>

// A utility function to get maximum of two integers
int max(int a, int b) { return (a > b)? a: b; }

/* Function to get minimum number of trails needed in worst
  case with n eggs and k floors */
int eggDrop(int n, int k)
{
    /* A 2D table where entery eggFloor[i][j] will represent minimum
       number of trials needed for i eggs and j floors. */
    int eggFloor[n+1][k+1];
    int res;
    int i, j, x;

    // We need one trial for one floor and0 trials for 0 floors
    for (i = 1; i <= n; i++)
    {
        eggFloor[i][1] = 1;
        eggFloor[i][0] = 0;
    }

    // We always need j trials for one egg and j floors.
    for (j = 1; j <= k; j++)
        eggFloor[1][j] = j;

    // Fill rest of the entries in table using optimal substructure
    // property
    for (i = 2; i <= n; i++)
    {
        for (j = 2; j <= k; j++)
        {
            eggFloor[i][j] = INT_MAX;
            for (x = 1; x <= j; x++)
            {
                res = 1 + max(eggFloor[i-1][x-1], eggFloor[i][j-x]);
                if (res < eggFloor[i][j])
                    eggFloor[i][j] = res;
            }
        }
    }

    // eggFloor[n][k] holds the result
    return eggFloor[n][k];
}

/* Driver program to test to pront printDups*/
int main()
{
    int n = 2, k = 36;
    printf ("\nMinimum number of trials in worst case with %d eggs and "
             "%d floors is %d \n", n, k, eggDrop(n, k));
    return 0;
}
 

 Output:
Minimum number of trials in worst case with 2 eggs and 36 floors is 8
 

Time Complexity: O(nk^2)
Auxiliary Space: O(nk)

As an exercise, you may try modifying the above DP solution to print all intermediate floors (The floors used for minimum trail solution).

References:
http://archive.ite.journal.informs.org/Vol4No1/Sniedovich/index.php

Please write comments if you find anything incorrect, or you want to share more information about the topic discussed above.

Source

http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/dynamic-programming-set-11-egg-dropping-puzzle/

Dynamic Programming | Set 28 (Minimum insertions to form a palindrome)

Given a string, find the minimum number of characters to be inserted to convert it to palindrome.

Before we go further, let us understand with few examples:
    ab: Number of insertions required is 1. bab
    aa: Number of insertions required is 0. aa
    abcd: Number of insertions required is 3. dcbabcd
    abcda: Number of insertions required is 2. adcbcda which is same as number of insertions in the substring bcd(Why?).
    abcde: Number of insertions required is 4. edcbabcde

Let the input string be str[l……h]. The problem can be broken down into three parts:
1. Find the minimum number of insertions in the substring str[l+1,…….h].
2. Find the minimum number of insertions in the substring str[l…….h-1].
3. Find the minimum number of insertions in the substring str[l+1……h-1].

Recursive Solution
The minimum number of insertions in the string str[l…..h] can be given as:
minInsertions(str[l+1…..h-1]) if str[l] is equal to str[h]
min(minInsertions(str[l…..h-1]), minInsertions(str[l+1…..h])) + 1 otherwise

 
// A Naive recursive program to find minimum number insertions
// needed to make a string palindrome
#include <stdio.h>
#include <limits.h>
#include <string.h>

// A utility function to find minimum of two numbers
int min(int a, int b)
{  return a < b ? a : b; }

// Recursive function to find minimum number of insersions
int findMinInsertions(char str[], int l, int h)
{
    // Base Cases
    if (l > h) return INT_MAX;
    if (l == h) return 0;
    if (l == h - 1) return (str[l] == str[h])? 0 : 1;

    // Check if the first and last characters are same. On the basis of the
    // comparison result, decide which subrpoblem(s) to call
    return (str[l] == str[h])? findMinInsertions(str, l + 1, h - 1):
                               (min(findMinInsertions(str, l, h - 1),
                                   findMinInsertions(str, l + 1, h)) + 1);
}

// Driver program to test above functions
int main()
{
    char str[] = "geeks";
    printf("%d", findMinInsertions(str, 0, strlen(str)-1));
    return 0;
}
 

Output:

 3 

Dynamic Programming based Solution
If we observe the above approach carefully, we can find that it exhibits overlapping subproblems.
Suppose we want to find the minimum number of insertions in string “abcde”:

                       abcde
            /       |      \
           /        |        \
           bcde         abcd       bcd  <- case 3 is discarded as str[l] != str[h]
       /   |   \       /   |   \
      /    |    \     /    |    \
     cde   bcd  cd   bcd abc bc
   / | \  / | \ /|\ / | \
de cd d cd bc c…………………. 

The substrings in bold show that the recursion to be terminated and the recursion tree cannot originate from there. Substring in the same color indicates overlapping subproblems.

How to reuse solutions of subproblems?
We can create a table to store results of subproblems so that they can be used directly if same subproblem is encountered again.

The below table represents the stored values for the string abcde.

 a b c d e
----------
0 1 2 3 4
0 0 1 2 3 
0 0 0 1 2 
0 0 0 0 1 
0 0 0 0 0 

How to fill the table?
The table should be filled in diagonal fashion. For the string abcde, 0….4, the following should be order in which the table is filled:

 
Gap = 1:
(0, 1) (1, 2) (2, 3) (3, 4)

Gap = 2:
(0, 2) (1, 3) (2, 4)

Gap = 3:
(0, 3) (1, 4)

Gap = 4:
(0, 4) 

 
// A Dynamic Programming based program to find minimum number
// insertions needed to make a string palindrome
#include <stdio.h>
#include <string.h>

// A utility function to find minimum of two integers
int min(int a, int b)
{   return a < b ? a : b;  }

// A DP function to find minimum number of insersions
int findMinInsertionsDP(char str[], int n)
{
    // Create a table of size n*n. table[i][j] will store
    // minumum number of insertions needed to convert str[i..j]
    // to a palindrome.
    int table[n][n], l, h, gap;

    // Initialize all table entries as 0
    memset(table, 0, sizeof(table));

    // Fill the table
    for (gap = 1; gap < n; ++gap)
        for (l = 0, h = gap; h < n; ++l, ++h)
            table[l][h] = (str[l] == str[h])? table[l+1][h-1] :
                          (min(table[l][h-1], table[l+1][h]) + 1);

    // Return minimum number of insertions for str[0..n-1]
    return table[0][n-1];
}

// Driver program to test above function.
int main()
{
    char str[] = "geeks";
    printf("%d", findMinInsertionsDP(str, strlen(str)));
    return 0;
}
 

Output:

 3 

Time complexity: O(N^2)
Auxiliary Space: O(N^2)

Another Dynamic Programming Solution (Variation of Longest Common Subsequence Problem)
The problem of finding minimum insertions can also be solved using Longest Common Subsequence (LCS) Problem. If we find out LCS of string and its reverse, we know how many maximum characters can form a palindrome. We need insert remaining characters. Following are the steps.
1) Find the length of LCS of input string and its reverse. Let the length be ‘l’.
2) The minimum number insertions needed is length of input string minus ‘l’.

 
// An LCS based program to find minimum number insertions needed to
// make a string palindrome
#include<stdio.h>
#include <string.h>

/* Utility function to get max of 2 integers */
int max(int a, int b)
{   return (a > b)? a : b; }

/* Returns length of LCS for X[0..m-1], Y[0..n-1]. 
   See http://goo.gl/bHQVP for details of this function */
int lcs( char *X, char *Y, int m, int n )
{
   int L[n+1][n+1];
   int i, j;

   /* Following steps build L[m+1][n+1] in bottom up fashion. Note
      that L[i][j] contains length of LCS of X[0..i-1] and Y[0..j-1] */
   for (i=0; i<=m; i++)
   {
     for (j=0; j<=n; j++)
     {
       if (i == 0 || j == 0)
         L[i][j] = 0;

       else if (X[i-1] == Y[j-1])
         L[i][j] = L[i-1][j-1] + 1;

       else
         L[i][j] = max(L[i-1][j], L[i][j-1]);
     }
   }

   /* L[m][n] contains length of LCS for X[0..n-1] and Y[0..m-1] */
   return L[m][n];
}

// LCS based function to find minimum number of insersions
int findMinInsertionsLCS(char str[], int n)
{
   // Creata another string to store reverse of 'str'
   char rev[n+1];
   strcpy(rev, str);
   strrev(rev);

   // The output is length of string minus length of lcs of
   // str and it reverse
   return (n - lcs(str, rev, n, n));
}

// Driver program to test above functions
int main()
{
    char str[] = "geeks";
    printf("%d", findMinInsertionsLCS(str, strlen(str)));
    return 0;
}
 

Output:

 3 

Time complexity of this method is also O(n^2) and this method also requires O(n^2) extra space.

This article is compiled by Aashish Barnwal. Please write comments if you find anything incorrect, or you want to share more information about the topic discussed above

Source

http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/dynamic-programming-set-28-minimum-insertions-to-form-a-palindrome/

Category: Misc Tags: Dynamic Programming

Post navigation

← Longest prefix matching – A Trie based solution in Java Dynamic Programming | Set 29 (Longest Common Substring) →

Writing code in comment? Please use code.geeksforgeeks.org, generate link and share the link here.

Shortest Common Supersequence

Given two strings str1 and str2, find the shortest string that has both str1 and str2 as subsequences.

Examples:

 
Input:   str1 = "geek",  str2 = "eke"
Output: "geeke"

Input:   str1 = "AGGTAB",  str2 = "GXTXAYB"
Output:  "AGXGTXAYB"
 

We strongly recommend you to minimize your browser and try this yourself first.

This problem is closely related to longest common subsequence problem. Below are steps.

1) Find Longest Common Subsequence (lcs) of two given strings. For example, lcs of “geek” and “eke” is “ek”.

2) Insert non-lcs characters (in their original order in strings) to the lcs found above, and return the result. So “ek” becomes “geeke” which is shortest common supersequence.

Let us consider another example, str1 = “AGGTAB” and str2 = “GXTXAYB”. LCS of str1 and str2 is “GTAB”. Once we find LCS, we insert characters of both strings in order and we get “AGXGTXAYB”

How does this work?
We need to find a string that has both strings as subsequences and is shortest such string. If both strings have all characters different, then result is sum of lengths of two given strings. If there are common characters, then we don’t want them multiple times as the task is to minimize length. Therefore, we fist find the longest common subsequence, take one occurrence of this subsequence and add extra characters.

 

Length of the shortest supersequence  = (Sum of lengths of given two strings) - 
                                        (Length of LCS of two given strings)  

Below is C implementation of above idea. The below implementation only finds length of the shortest supersequence.

 
/* C program to find length of the shortest supersequence */
#include<stdio.h>
#include<string.h>

/* Utility function to get max of 2 integers */
int max(int a, int b) { return (a > b)? a : b; }

/* Returns length of LCS for X[0..m-1], Y[0..n-1] */
int lcs( char *X, char *Y, int m, int n);

// Function to find length of the shortest supersequence
// of X and Y.
int shortestSuperSequence(char *X, char *Y)
{
  int m = strlen(X), n = strlen(Y);

  int l = lcs(X, Y, m, n); // find lcs

  // Result is sum of input string lengths - length of lcs
  return (m + n - l);
}

/* Returns length of LCS for X[0..m-1], Y[0..n-1] */
int lcs( char *X, char *Y, int m, int n)
{
   int L[m+1][n+1];
   int i, j;

   /* Following steps build L[m+1][n+1] in bottom up fashion.
      Note that L[i][j] contains length of LCS of X[0..i-1]
      and Y[0..j-1] */
   for (i=0; i<=m; i++)
   {
     for (j=0; j<=n; j++)
     {
       if (i == 0 || j == 0)
         L[i][j] = 0;

       else if (X[i-1] == Y[j-1])
         L[i][j] = L[i-1][j-1] + 1;

       else
         L[i][j] = max(L[i-1][j], L[i][j-1]);
     }
   }

   /* L[m][n] contains length of LCS for X[0..n-1] and
      Y[0..m-1] */
   return L[m][n];
}

/* Driver program to test above function */
int main()
{
  char X[] = "AGGTAB";
  char Y[] = "GXTXAYB";
  printf("Length of the shortest supersequence is %d\n",
         shortestSuperSequence(X, Y));
  return 0;
}
 

Output:

 Length of the shortest supersequence is 9 

Below is Another Method to solve the above problem.
A simple analysis yields below simple recursive solution.

 
Let X[0..m-1] and Y[0..n-1] be two strings and m and be respective 
lengths.

  if (m == 0) return n;
  if (n == 0) return m;

  // If last characters are same, then add 1 to result and
  // recur for X[]
  if (X[m-1] == Y[n-1]) 
     return 1 + SCS(X, Y, m-1, n-1);

  // Else find shortest of following two
  //  a) Remove last character from X and recur
  //  b) Remove last character from Y and recur
  else return 1 + min( SCS(X, Y, m-1, n), SCS(X, Y, m, n-1) );
 

Below is simple naive recursive solution based on above recursive formula.

 
/* A Naive recursive C++ program to find length
   of the shortest supersequence */
#include<bits/stdc++.h>
using namespace std;

int superSeq(char* X, char* Y, int m, int n)
{
    if (!m) return n;
    if (!n) return m;

    if (X[m-1] == Y[n-1])
        return 1 + superSeq(X, Y, m-1, n-1);

    return 1 + min(superSeq(X, Y, m-1, n),
                   superSeq(X, Y, m, n-1));
}

// Driver program to test above function
int main()
{
    char X[] = "AGGTAB";
    char Y[] = "GXTXAYB";
    cout << "Length of the shortest supersequence is "
         << superSeq(X, Y, strlen(X), strlen(Y));
    return 0;
}
 

Output:

 Length of the shortest supersequence is 9 

Time complexity of the above solution exponential O(2min(m, n)). Since there are overlapping subproblems, we can efficiently solve this recursive problem using Dynamic Programming. Below is Dynamic Programming based implementation. Time complexity of this solution is O(mn).

 
/* A dynamic programming based C program to find length
   of the shortest supersequence */
#include<bits/stdc++.h>
using namespace std;

// Returns length of the shortest supersequence of X and Y
int superSeq(char* X, char* Y, int m, int n)
{
    int dp[m+1][n+1];

    // Fill table in bottom up manner
    for (int i = 0; i <= m; i++)
    {
        for (int j = 0; j <= n; j++)
        {
           // Below steps follow above recurrence
           if (!i)
               dp[i][j] = j;
           else if (!j)
               dp[i][j] = i;
           else if (X[i-1] == Y[j-1])
                dp[i][j] = 1 + dp[i-1][j-1];
           else
                dp[i][j] = 1 + min(dp[i-1][j], dp[i][j-1]);
        }
    }

    return dp[m][n];
}

// Driver program to test above function
int main()
{
    char X[] = "AGGTAB";
    char Y[] = "GXTXAYB";
    cout << "Length of the shortest supersequence is "
         << superSeq(X, Y, strlen(X), strlen(Y));
    return 0;
} 

Output:

 Length of the shortest supersequence is 9 

Thanks to Gaurav Ahirwar for suggesting this solution.

Exercise:
Extend the above program to print shortest supersequence also using function to print LCS.

References:
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortest_common_supersequence

Please write comments if you find anything incorrect, or you want to share more information about the topic discussed above

Source

http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/shortest-common-supersequence/

Category: Strings Tags: Dynamic Programming

Post navigation

← Count BST subtrees that lie in given range Shortest Superstring Problem →

Writing code in comment? Please use code.geeksforgeeks.org, generate link and share the link here.

Minimum Initial Points to Reach Destination

Given a grid with each cell consisting of positive, negative or no points i.e, zero points. We can move across a cell only if we have positive points ( > 0 ). Whenever we pass through a cell, points in that cell are added to our overall points. We need to find minimum initial points to reach cell (m-1, n-1) from (0, 0).

Constraints :

From a cell (i, j) we can move to (i+1, j) or (i, j+1).
We cannot move from (i, j) if your overall points at (i, j) is
We have to reach at (n-1, m-1) with minimum positive points i.e., > 0.

 
Input: points[m][n] = { {-2, -3,   3}, 
                        {-5, -10,  1}, 
                        {10,  30, -5} 
                      };
Output: 7
Explanation: 
7 is the minimum value to reach destination with 
positive throughout the path. Below is the path.

(0,0) -> (0,1) -> (0,2) -> (1, 2) -> (2, 2)

We start from (0, 0) with 7, we reach(0, 1) 
with 5, (0, 2) with 2, (1, 2) with 5, (2, 2)
with and finally we have 1 point (we needed 
greater than 0 points at the end).  

We strongly recommend you to minimize your browser and try this yourself first.

At the first look, this problem looks similar Max/Min Cost Path, but maximum overall points gained will not guarantee the minimum initial points. Also, it is compulsory in the current problem that the points never drops to zero or below. For instance, Suppose following two paths exists from source to destination cell.

We can solve this problem through bottom-up table filling dynamic programing technique.

To begin with, we should maintain a 2D array dp of the same size as the grid, where dp[i][j] represents the minimum points that guarantees the continuation of the journey to destination before entering the cell (i, j). It’s but obvious that dp[0][0] is our final solution. Hence, for this problem, we need to fill the table from the bottom right corner to left top.
Now, let us decide minimum points needed to leave cell (i, j) (remember we are moving from bottom to up). There are only two paths to choose: (i+1, j) and (i, j+1). Of course we will choose the cell that the player can finish the rest of his journey with a smaller initial points. Therefore we have: min_Points_on_exit = min(dp[i+1][j], dp[i][j+1])

Now we know how to compute min_Points_on_exit, but we need to fill the table dp[][] to get the solution in dp[0][0].

How to compute dp[i][j]?
     The value of dp[i][j] can be written as below.

dp[i][j] = max(min_Points_on_exit – points[i][j], 1)

Let us see how above expression covers all cases.

If points[i][j] == 0, then nothing is gained in this cell; the player can leave the cell with the same points as he enters the room with, i.e. dp[i][j] = min_Points_on_exit.
If dp[i][j] If dp[i][j] > 0, then the player could enter (i, j) with points as little as min_Points_on_exit – points[i][j]. since he could gain “points[i][j]” points in this cell. However, the value of min_Points_on_exit – points[i][j] might drop to 0 or below in this situation. When this happens, we must clip the value to 1 in order to make sure dp[i][j] stays positive:
dp[i][j] = max(min_Points_on_exit – points[i][j], 1).

Finally return dp[0][0] which is our answer.

Below is C++ implementation of above algorithm.

 
// C++ program to find minimum initial points to reach destination
#include<bits/stdc++.h>
#define R 3
#define C 3
using namespace std;

int minInitialPoints(int points[][C])
{
    // dp[i][j] represents the minimum initial points player
    // should have so that when starts with cell(i, j) successfully
    // reaches the destination cell(m-1, n-1)
    int dp[R][C];
    int m = R, n = C;

    // Base case
    dp[m-1][n-1] = points[m-1][n-1] > 0? 1:
                   abs(points[m-1][n-1]) + 1;

    // Fill last row and last column as base to fill
    // entire table
    for (int i = m-2; i >= 0; i--)
         dp[i][n-1] = max(dp[i+1][n-1] - points[i][n-1], 1);
    for (int j = n-2; j >= 0; j--)
         dp[m-1][j] = max(dp[m-1][j+1] - points[m-1][j], 1);

    // fill the table in bottom-up fashion
    for (int i=m-2; i>=0; i--)
    {
        for (int j=n-2; j>=0; j--)
        {
            int min_points_on_exit = min(dp[i+1][j], dp[i][j+1]);
            dp[i][j] = max(min_points_on_exit - points[i][j], 1);
        }
     }

     return dp[0][0];
}

// Driver Program
int main()
{

    int points[R][C] = { {-2,-3,3},
                      {-5,-10,1},
                      {10,30,-5}
                    };
    cout << "Minimum Initial Points Required: "
         << minInitialPoints(points);
    return 0;
}
 

Output:

 Minimum Initial Points Required: 7 

This article is contributed by Gaurav Ahirwar. Please write comments if you find anything incorrect, or you want to share more information about the topic discussed above

Source

http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/minimum-positive-points-to-reach-destination/

Category: Arrays Tags: Dynamic Programming, Matrix

Post navigation

← Amazon Interview Experience | Set 227 (On-Campus for Internship and Full-Time) Count of n digit numbers whose sum of digits equals to given sum →

Writing code in comment? Please use code.geeksforgeeks.org, generate link and share the link here.

Bitmasking and Dynamic Programming | Set 1 (Count ways to assign unique cap to every person)

Consider the below problems statement.

There 100 different types of caps each having a unique id from 1 to 100. Also, there ‘n’ persons each having a collection of variable number of caps. One day all of these persons decide to go in a party wearing a cap but to look unique they decided that none them will wear the same type of cap. So, count the total number of arrangements or ways such that none of them is wearing same type of cap.

Constraints: 1 First line contains value of n, next n lines contain collections of all the n persons. Input: 3 5 100 1 // Collection of first person. 2 // Collection of second person. 5 100 // Collection of second person. Output: 4 Explanation: All valid possible ways are (5, 2, 100), (100, 2, 5), (1, 2, 5) and (1, 2, 100)

Since, number of ways could be large, so output modulo 1000000007

We strongly recommend you to minimize your browser and try this yourself first.
A Simple Solution is to try all possible combinations. Start by picking first element from first set, marking it as visited and recur for remaining sets. It is basically a Backtracking based solution.

A better solution is to use Bitmasking and DP. Let us first introduce Bitmasking.

What is Bitmasking?
Suppose we have a collection of elements which are numbered from 1 to N. If we want to represent a subset of this set than it can be encoded by a sequence of N bits (we usually call this sequence a “mask”). In our chosen subset the i-th element belongs to it if and only if the i-th bit of the mask I set i.e., it equals to 1. For example, the mask 10000101 means that the subset of the set [1… 8] consists of elements 1, 3 and 8. We know that for a set of N elements there are total 2N subsets thus 2N masks are possible, one representing each subset. Each mask is in fact an integer number written in binary notation.

Our main methodology is to assign a value to each mask (and, therefore, to each subset) and thus calculate the values for new masks using values of the already computed masks. Usually our main target is to calculate value/solution for the complete set i.e., for mask 11111111. Normally, to find the value for a subset X we remove an element in every possible way and use values for obtained subsets X’1, X’2… ,X’k to compute the value/solution for X. This means that the values for X’i must have been computed already, so we need to establish an ordering in which masks will be considered. It’s easy to see that the natural ordering will do: go over masks in increasing order of corresponding numbers. Also, We sometimes, start with the empty subset X and we add elements in every possible way and use the values of obtained subsets X’1, X’2… ,X’k to compute the value/solution for X.

We mostly use the following notations/operations on masks:
bit(i,mask) – the i-th bit of mask
count(mask) – the number of non-zero bits in mask
first(mask) – the number of the lowest non-zero bit in mask
set(i, mask) – set the ith bit in mask
check(i, mask) – check the ith bit in mask

How is this problem solved using Bitmasking + DP?
The idea is to use the fact that there are upto 10 persons. So we can use a integer variable as a bitmask to store which person is wearing cap and which is not.

 
Let i be the current cap number (caps from 1 to i-1 are already 
processed). Let integer variable mask indicates the the persons w
earing and not wearing caps.  If i'th bit is set in mask, then 
i'th person is wearing a cap, else not.

             // consider the case when ith cap is not included 
                     // in the arrangement
countWays(mask, i) = countWays(mask, i+1) +             
                    
                    // when ith cap is included in the arrangement
                    // so, assign this cap to all possible persons 
                    // one by one and recur for remaining persons.
                    &Sum; countWays(mask | (1 
If we draw the complete recursion tree, we can observer that many subproblems are solved again and again.  So we use Dynamic Programming.  A table dp[][] is used such that in every entry dp[i][j], i is mask and j is cap number. 
Since we want to access all persons that can wear a given cap, we use an array of vectors, capList[101].  A value capList[i] indicates the list of persons that can wear cap i.
Below is C++ implementation of above idea.
 
// C++ program to find number of ways to wear hats
#include<bits/stdc++.h>
#define MOD 1000000007
using namespace std;

// capList[i]'th vector contains the list of persons having a cap with id i
// id is between 1 to 100 so we declared an array of 101 vectors as indexing
// starts from 0.
vector<int> capList[101];

// dp[2^10][101] .. in dp[i][j], i denotes the mask i.e., it tells that
// how many and which persons are wearing cap. j denotes the first j caps
// used. So, dp[i][j] tells the number ways we assign j caps to mask i
// such that none of them wears the same cap
int dp[1025][101];

// This is used for base case, it has all the N bits set
// so, it tells whether all N persons are wearing a cap.
int allmask;

// Mask is the set of persons, i is the number of
// caps processed starting from first cap.
long long int countWaysUtil(int mask, int i)
{
    // If all persons are wearing a cap so we
    // are done and this is one way so return 1
    if (mask == allmask) return 1;

    // If not everyone is wearing a cap and also there are no more
    // caps left to process, so there is no way, thus return 0;
    if (i > 100) return 0;

    // If we already have solved this subproblem, return the answer.
    if (dp[mask][i] != -1) return dp[mask][i];

    // Ways, when we don't include this cap in our arrangement
    // or solution set.
    long long int ways = countWaysUtil(mask, i+1);

    // size is the total number of persons having cap with id i.
    int size = capList[i].size();

    // So, assign one by one ith cap to all the possible persons
    // and recur for remaining caps.
    for (int j = 0; j < size; j++)
    {
        // if person capList[i][j] is already wearing a cap so continue as
        // we cannot assign him this cap
        if (mask & (1 << capList[i][j])) continue;

        // Else assign him this cap and recur for remaining caps with
        // new updated mask vector
        else ways += countWaysUtil(mask | (1 << capList[i][j]), i+1);
        ways %= MOD;
    }

    // Save the result and return it.
    return dp[mask][i] = ways;
}

// Reads n lines from standard input for current test case
void countWays(int n)
{
    //----------- READ INPUT --------------------------
    string temp, str;
    int x;
    getline(cin, str);  // to get rid of newline character
    for (int i=0; i<n; i++)
    {
        getline(cin, str);
        stringstream ss(str);

        // while there are words in the streamobject ss
        while (ss >> temp)
        {
            stringstream s;
            s << temp;
            s >> x;

            // add the ith person in the list of cap if with id x
            capList[x].push_back(i);
        }
    }
    //----------------------------------------------------

    // All mask is used to check of all persons
    // are included or not, set all n bits as 1
    allmask = (1 << n) - 1;

    // Initialize all entries in dp as -1
    memset(dp, -1, sizeof dp);

    // Call recursive function count ways
    cout << countWaysUtil(0, 1) << endl;
}

// Driver Program
int main()
{ 
     int n;   // number of persons in every test case
     cin >> n;
     countWays(n);
     return 0;
}
 

Input:

 
3               
5 100 1         
2               
5 100 

Output:

 
4 

This article is contributed by Gaurav Ahirwar. Please write comments if you find anything incorrect, or you want to share more information about the topic discussed above

Source

http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/bitmasking-and-dynamic-programming-set-1-count-ways-to-assign-unique-cap-to-every-person/